Do you want subtitles for any video?
-=[ ai.OpenSubtitles.com ]=-
[GRUNTING]
[GIBBERS]
[GIBBERING AND GRUNTING]
[LEOPARD ROARS
THEN APE MAN SCREAMING]
[LEOPARD GROWLING]
[APE MAN SHRIEKS
THEN APE MEN GIBBERING]
[GRUNTING]
[GROWLS]
[APE MEN SCREAM]
Here you are, sir.
Main level, please.
Right. See you on the way back.
- Bye.
RECEPTIONIST: Good morning, sir.
FLOYD: Morning.
- We haven't seen you for a long time.
- Nice to see you again.
- Did you have a pleasant flight?
- Very nice.
Mr. Miller of Station Security
is supposed to meet me.
- May I call him for you?
- Would you? Here he is.
- Hello, Dr. Floyd.
- Hello, Miller.
MILLER: Sorry I'm late.
FLOYD: That's all right.
MILLER:
It's nice to have you back.
- Did you have a good flight?
- Very nice.
- Shall we go through?
- Would you please use number 17?
MILLER: Thank you, Ms. Turner. This way.
FLOYD: Thank you.
Welcome to Voiceprint Identification.
When you see the red light go on,
please state in the following order:
Your destination,
your nationality and your full name.
Surname first, Christian name,
and initial.
Moon. American. Floyd, Heywood R.
Thank you. You are cleared through
Voiceprint Identification.
Thank you.
FLOYD: Have I got time for breakfast?
MILLER: I think we can manage that.
FLOYD:
How long have I got?
MILLER: Your flight leaves
in an hour and 10 minutes.
I've reserved a table for you
in the Earthlight Room.
It's been seven or eight months
since you were here, hasn't it?
FLOYD:
Let's see. Yeah, about eight months.
MILLER: I suppose you saw the work
on the new section?
FLOYD: Coming along great, huh?
MILLER: Yeah, it's fine.
FLOYD:
Oh, wait.
I've got to make a couple calls.
I'll meet you in the restaurant.
- Dad?
- Hello.
Hi, squirt.
What are you doing?
Playing.
Where's Mummy?
Gone to shopping.
- Who's taking care of you?
- Rachel.
- May I speak to Rachel, please?
- She's gone to the bathroom.
Are you coming
to my party tomorrow?
I'm sorry, sweetheart, but I can't.
Why not?
Well, you know, Daddy's traveling.
Very sorry about it, but I just can't.
I'm going to send you
a very nice present, though.
All right.
- Anything special that you want?
- Yes.
What?
A telephone.
We've got lots of telephones already.
Can't you think of anything else
for your birthday? Something special?
- Yes.
- What?
A bush baby.
A bush baby?
We'll have to see about that.
I want you to tell Mummy
something for me. Will you remember?
Tell Mummy that I telephoned. Okay?
And that I'll try
to telephone again tomorrow.
Now, will you tell her that?
Yes.
Okay, sweetheart.
Have a nice birthday tomorrow.
All right.
And have a nice birthday party
tomorrow too, huh?
All right.
Take care and be a good girl,
won't you?
All right. Bye-bye.
Bye-bye. Happy birthday.
[IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
FLOYD: Elena, nice to see you again.
ELENA: Heywood, what a surprise.
FLOYD: You're looking wonderful.
ELENA: You're looking well too.
ELENA: This is my friend,
Dr. Heywood Floyd.
ELENA: I'd like you to meet Dr. Kalinan.
FLOYD: How do you do?
ELENA: Dr. Stretyneva.
ELENA:
And this is Dr. Andrei Smyslov.
FLOYD: How do you do?
I've heard a lot about you.
SMYSLOV:
Do sit down.
FLOYD: Well, we...
SMYSLOV: No, no, please.
FLOYD:
Thank you.
SMYSLOV: Would you like a drink?
FLOYD: No, thank you.
I haven't had breakfast yet.
Someone's meeting me in the restaurant.
I'll just sit with you a moment.
Then I'll be off.
SMYSLOV: Are you quite sure?
FLOYD: Quite sure, thank you.
- Well, how's Gregor?
- He's fine.
He's been doing underwater research
in the Baltic...
...so I'm afraid we don't see
very much of each other these days.
- When you see him, give him my regards.
- Yes, of course.
Well, where are you all off to?
Up or down?
We're going home.
We've spent three months calibrating
the new antenna at Tchalinko.
- What about you?
- I'm on my way to Clavius.
Oh, are you?
Dr. Floyd, I hope you don't think
I'm being too inquisitive...
...but perhaps you can clear up the big
mystery about what is going on there.
I'm afraid I don't know
what you mean.
For the past two weeks...
...some extremely odd things
have been happening at Clavius.
- Oh, really?
- Yes, yes.
For one thing, when you phone the base,
all you get is a recording...
...which repeats that the phone lines
are temporarily out of order.
Probably having some trouble
with their equipment.
Yes.
That's what we thought at first,
but it's been going on now for 10 days.
You haven't been able to
contact anyone for 10 days?
That's right.
Oh, I see.
There's another thing.
Two days ago, one of our rocket buses...
...was denied permission
for an emergency landing.
That does sound odd.
I'm afraid there's going to be
a bit of a row about it.
Denying the men permission to land
violates the IAS Convention.
Yes, of course.
Did the crew get back all right?
- Fortunately, they did.
- Well, I'm glad about that.
At the risk of pressing you on
a point you seem reticent to discuss...
...may I ask you
a straightforward question?
Well, certainly.
Frankly, we have had some
very reliable intelligence reports that...
...quite a serious epidemic
has broken out at Clavius.
Something, apparently,
of an unknown origin.
Is this, in fact, what has happened?
I'm sorry, Dr. Smyslov, but...
...I'm really not at liberty
to discuss this.
I understand.
But this epidemic
could easily spread to our base.
We should be given all the facts.
Yes, I know.
As I said,
I'm not at liberty to discuss it.
Won't you change your mind
about that drink?
No, I'm positive.
I really must be going.
I hope you and your wife come
to the IAC Conference.
I hope we can make it.
If you do, bring that darling
little daughter with you.
That'll depend on school vacations
and all that sort of thing.
If we can, we will.
You've got an invitation
if you ever get to the States.
Gregor and I will look forward
to seeing you.
Goodbye, Elena.
It's been a pleasure meeting you all.
Dr. Smyslov.
Whatever the reasons for your visit,
the very best of luck to you.
Thank you.
Ladies.
[IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
[INAUDIBLE DIALOGUE]
[INDISTINCT CHATTER]
PHOTOGRAPHER:
Excuse me, Dr. Halvorsen.
I'm through now.
Thank you very much, gentlemen.
HALVORSEN:
You're welcome.
Well...
...I know you will all
want to join with me...
...in welcoming our distinguished
friend and colleague...
...from the National Council
of Astronautics, Dr. Heywood Floyd.
Dr. Floyd has come up specially
to Clavius to be with us today.
Before the briefing, he'd like
to have a few words with you.
Dr. Floyd?
FLOYD:
Thank you, Dr. Halvorsen.
Hi, everybody.
Nice to be back with you.
First, I bring a personal message
from Dr. Howell...
...who has asked me to convey
his deep appreciation...
...for the many sacrifices
you've had to make.
And, of course, his congratulations
on your discovery...
...which may prove to be among the most
significant in the history of science.
Now...
...I know there have been some
conflicting views...
...regarding the need for
complete security in this matter.
More specifically, your opposition
to the cover story...
...created to give the impression
of an epidemic at the base.
I understand that beyond it being
a matter of principle...
...many of you are troubled
by the concern and anxiety...
...this story of an epidemic might cause
to your relatives and friends on Earth.
I completely sympathize
with your negative views.
I find this cover story
personally embarrassing, myself.
However, I accept the need
for absolute secrecy in this.
And I hope you will too.
I'm sure you're all aware
of the grave potential...
...for cultural shock
and social disorientation...
...contained in this situation...
...if the facts were
prematurely made public...
...without adequate preparation
and conditioning.
Anyway...
...this is the view of the Council.
The purpose of my visit is to gather
additional facts and opinions...
...on the situation...
...and to prepare a report
to the Council...
...recommending when and how
the news should eventually be announced.
If any of you would like to give me
your views and opinions...
...in private, if you like, I will be
happy to include them in my report.
Well, I think that's about it.
Any questions?
Dr. Floyd, have you any idea
how much longer...
...this cover story will
have to be maintained?
FLOYD:
I don't know, Bill.
I suppose for as long as
deemed necessary by the Council.
There must be adequate time for
a full study...
...before any thought can be given
to making a public announcement.
As some of you know,
the Council has requested...
...that security oaths
be obtained in writing...
...from everyone who has
knowledge of this event.
Were there any more questions?
HALVORSEN: I'm sure
we want to cooperate with Dr. Floyd...
...as fully as possible...
...and as there are no more questions,
we ought to get on with the briefing.
HALVORSEN: Thank you, Dr. Floyd.
FLOYD: Thank you.
MICHAELS:
Anybody hungry?
FLOYD: What've we got?
MICHAELS: You name it.
FLOYD: Is this chicken?
MICHAELS: Something like that.
MICHAELS:
Tastes the same, anyway.
HALVORSEN:
Got any ham?
MICHAELS:
Ham, ham, ham...
HALVORSEN:
There, that's it.
Look pretty good.
MICHAELS: They're getting better at it
all the time.
HALVORSEN:
That was an excellent speech.
MICHAELS:
It certainly was.
I'm sure it beefed up morale a lot.
Thanks, Ralph.
By the way,
you've both done a wonderful job.
I admire how
you've handled this.
HALVORSEN: It's our job to do this thing
the way you want it done.
We're only too happy to
be able to oblige.
MICHAELS:
Have you seen these yet?
HALVORSEN: Have a look.
MICHAELS: Here's what started it all.
FLOYD:
Oh, yeah.
HALVORSEN:
When we found it...
...we thought
it might be magnetic rock...
...but all the geological evidence
was against it.
And not even a nickel-iron meteorite
could produce a field this intense.
So we decided to have a look.
MICHAELS: We thought it was
part of a buried structure...
...so we excavated out,
but we didn't find anything else.
HALVORSEN: And the evidence seems
pretty conclusive that...
...it hasn't been covered
by erosion or other forces.
It's been deliberately buried.
Deliberately buried.
MICHAELS:
How about a little coffee?
FLOYD: Great.
HALVORSEN: Good idea.
I don't suppose you have any idea
what the damn thing is?
HALVORSEN:
I wish to hell we did.
The only thing we're sure of is
it was buried 4 million years ago.
Well, I must say, you guys have
certainly come up with something.
MICHAELS:
Watch this, now. It's hot.
[BEEPING]
[HIGH-PITCHED NOISE]
NEWSCASTER:
Good evening.
Three weeks ago,
the American spacecraft Discovery One...
...left on its half-billion-mile voyage
to Jupiter.
This marked the first manned attempt
to reach this distant planet.
This afternoon, The World Tonight
recorded an interview...
...with the crew at a distance
of 80 million miles from Earth.
It took seven minutes for our words
to reach the giant spacecraft...
...but this time delay has been edited
from this recording.
Our reporter Martin Amer
speaks to the crew.
REPORTER: The crew of Discovery One
consists of five men...
...and one of the latest generation
of the HAL 9000 computers.
Three of the men
were put aboard asleep...
...or to be more precise,
in a state of hibernation.
They were Dr. Charles Hunter,
Dr. Jack Kimball...
...and Dr. Victor Kaminsky.
We spoke with mission commander,
Dr. David Bowman...
...and his deputy, Dr. Frank Poole.
Good afternoon, gentlemen.
How is everything going?
BOWMAN:
Marvelous.
We have no complaints.
I'm glad to hear that.
I'm sure the entire world...
...joins me in wishing you
a safe, successful voyage.
BOWMAN: Thanks very much.
POOLE: Thank you.
Although hibernation has been used
on previous space efforts...
...this is the first time men were
put into hibernation before departure.
Why was this done?
BOWMAN: This was done to achieve
the maximum conservation...
...of our life-support capabilities,
basically food and air.
The three hibernating crew members
represent the survey team.
Their efforts won't be utilized
until we approach Jupiter.
REPORTER: Dr. Poole, what's it like
while you're in hibernation?
It's exactly like being asleep.
You have no sense of time.
The only difference is
that you don't dream.
REPORTER: As I understand it, you only
breathe once a minute. Is this true?
POOLE: Right, and the heart
beats three times a minute.
Body temperature is usually down to
about three degrees centigrade.
REPORTER: The sixth member of the crew
was not concerned...
...about the problems of hibernation...
...for he was the latest result
in machine intelligence:
The HAL 9000 computer,
which can reproduce...
...though some experts prefer
to use the word "mimic"...
...most of the activities
of the human brain...
...and with incalculably greater
speed and reliability.
We next spoke with
the HAL 9000 computer...
...whom, we learned,
one addresses as "Hal."
Hello, Hal.
How's everything going?
HAL: Good afternoon, Mr. Amer.
Everything is going extremely well.
REPORTER: Hal, you have an enormous
responsibility on this mission...
...perhaps the greatest
of any single mission element.
You're the brain
and nervous system of the ship.
Your responsibilities include
watching over the men in hibernation.
Does this ever cause you
any lack of confidence?
HAL:
Let me put it this way, Mr. Amer.
The 9000 Series is
the most reliable computer ever made.
No 9000 computer has ever made
a mistake or distorted information.
We are all, by any practical
definition of the words...
...foolproof and incapable of error.
REPORTER: Hal, despite your enormous
intellect, are you ever frustrated...
...by your dependence on people
to carry out actions?
HAL:
Not in the slightest bit.
I enjoy working with people.
I have a stimulating relationship
with Dr. Poole and Dr. Bowman.
My mission responsibilities range
over the entire operation of the ship...
...so I am constantly occupied.
I am putting myself
to the fullest possible use...
...which is all, I think, that any
conscious entity can ever hope to do.
REPORTER: Dr. Poole, what's it like
living for most of the year...
...in such close proximity with Hal?
POOLE:
It's like what you said earlier.
He's like a sixth
member of the crew.
You quickly get adjusted to the idea
that he talks, and think of him...
...really just as another person.
REPORTER: In talking to the computer,
one gets the sense that he's capable...
...of emotional responses.
When I asked him
about his abilities...
...I sensed pride in his answer
about his accuracy and perfection.
Do you believe that Hal
has genuine emotions?
BOWMAN: Well, he acts like
he has genuine emotions.
He's programmed that way
to make it easier for us to talk to him.
As to whether or not
he has feelings...
...is something I don't think
anyone can truthfully answer.
HAL:
Excuse me, Frank.
What is it, Hal?
HAL: We've got the transmission
from your parents coming in.
Fine.
Put it on here, please.
Take me in a bit.
Certainly.
DAD: Hello, Frank.
MOM: Happy birthday, darling.
DAD: Happy birthday.
Many happy returns.
POOLE:
A bit higher, Hal.
DAD: Mother and I are both
feeling wonderful.
Ray and Sally were going
to be here...
...but Ray's back
went bad on him again.
How do you like your cake?
Sorry you can't join us.
I ran into Bob the other day.
He said to wish you happy birthday.
All my students
send their best wishes too.
They talk about you all the time.
You're a big celebrity
in the second grade.
MOM:
We were on TV last week.
DAD: Your mom and I
and Dave's parents were asked...
...what we thought
of our illustrious sons.
Imagine what we told them.
It's being broadcast next Thursday.
Perhaps you can listen in.
MOM:
We're thrilled about Elaine and Bill.
I'll be glad to get the gift,
but tell me how much to spend.
DAD: Oh, Frank,
about your AGS-19 payments...
...I think I straightened it out.
I talked to
the accounting office yesterday...
...and they said you'd be receiving
your higher rates of pay by next month.
I can't think of anything else to say.
MOM: Give our love to Dave.
DAD: Be sure to give him our regards.
DAD: We wish you the very
happiest of birthdays.
All the best, son.
MOM & DAD SING:
Happy birthday to you
Happy birthday, dear Frank
Happy birthday to you.
DAD:
See you next Wednesday.
HAL:
Happy birthday, Frank.
Thank you, Hal.
A bit flatter, please.
POOLE:
Anyway, queen takes pawn.
HAL:
Bishop takes knight's pawn.
POOLE:
Lovely move.
Rook to king one.
HAL: I'm sorry, Frank.
I think you missed it.
Queen to bishop three.
Bishop takes queen.
Knight takes bishop. Mate.
POOLE:
Looks like you're right. I resign.
HAL:
Thank you for a very enjoyable game.
POOLE:
Thank you.
HAL: Good evening, Dave.
BOWMAN: How are you, Hal?
- Everything's running smoothly, you?
BOWMAN: Not too bad.
- Have you been doing more work?
- A few sketches.
- May I see them?
- Sure.
That's a very nice rendering, Dave.
I think you've improved a great deal.
- Can you hold it a bit closer?
- Sure.
That's Dr. Hunter, isn't it?
By the way...
...do you mind if I ask you
a personal question?
No, not at all.
Well, forgive me
for being so inquisitive...
...but lately I've wondered...
...whether you might be having
second thoughts about the mission?
How do you mean?
Well, it's rather difficult to define.
Perhaps I'm just projecting
my own concern about it.
I know I've never completely
freed myself of the suspicion...
...that there are some extremely
odd things about this mission.
I'm sure you'll agree
there's some truth in what I say.
That's a rather difficult
question to answer.
You don't mind talking about it,
do you, Dave?
No, not at all.
Certainly no one could
have been unaware of the very...
...strange stories floating
around before we left.
Rumors about something
being dug up on the moon.
I never gave these stories
much credence...
...but particularly in view of some
other things that have happened...
...I find them difficult
to put out of my mind.
For instance...
...the way all our preparations
were kept under such tight security.
And the melodramatic touch
of putting Drs. Hunter...
...Kimball and Kaminsky aboard...
...already in hibernation, after four
months of training on their own.
You working up your crew
psychology report?
Of course I am.
Sorry about this.
I know it's a bit silly.
Just a moment.
I've just picked up a fault
in the AE-35 unit.
It's going to go 100-percent failure
within 72 hours.
- Is it still within operational limits?
- Yes.
And it will stay that way
until it fails.
We have 72 hours till failure?
Yes. That's a completely
reliable figure.
Then we'll bring it in.
I'll go over it with Frank...
...and get on to Mission Control.
Let me have the hard copy on it.
CONTROLLER: X-ray delta one,
this is Mission Control.
Roger your two-zero-one-three.
Sorry you fellows are having
a bit of trouble.
We're reviewing telemetric information
in our simulator and will advise.
Roger your plan to go EVA
and replace alpha-echo-three-five unit...
...prior to failure.
BOWMAN:
Prepare B-pod for EVA, Hal.
Open the pod doors, Hal.
I'm damned if I can find
anything wrong with it.
HAL:
Yes...
...it's puzzling.
I don't think I've ever seen
anything quite like this before.
I would recommend...
...that we put the unit back
in operation and let it fail.
It should then be a simple matter
to track down the cause.
We can certainly afford
to be out of communication...
...for the short time
it will take to replace it.
CONTROLLER: X-ray delta one,
this is Mission Control.
Roger your one-niner-three-zero.
We concur with your plan to replace
unit to check fault prediction.
We advise you that
our preliminary findings...
...indicate that your on board
9000 computer...
...is in error predicting the fault.
I say again, in error
predicting the fault.
I know this sounds rather incredible,
but this conclusion is based on...
...the results from our twin
9000 computer.
We're skeptical, and we're running
cross-checking routines...
...to determine reliability
of this conclusion.
Sorry about this little snag.
We'll get this info to you
as soon as we work it out.
X-ray delta one,
this is Mission Control.
Two-zero-four-nine.
Transmission concluded.
HAL: I hope the two of you
are not concerned about this.
No, I'm not, Hal.
Are you quite sure?
- Yeah. I'd like to ask you a question.
- Of course.
How do you account for the discrepancy
between you and the twin 9000?
Well, I don't think there is
any question about it.
It can only be
attributable to human error.
This sort of thing
has cropped up before...
...and it has always
been due to human error.
Listen, Hal...
...there's never been
any instance at all...
...of a computer error
occurring in a 9000 Series, has there?
None whatsoever, Frank.
The 9000 Series has
a perfect operational record.
POOLE: I know the wonderful
achievements of the 9000 Series, but...
Are you certain there's never been even
the most insignificant computer error?
None whatsoever, Frank.
Quite honestly, I wouldn't
worry myself about that.
Well, I'm sure you're right, Hal.
Fine. Thanks very much.
I'm having trouble
with my transmitter in C-pod.
Would you come down
and take a look at it with me?
See you later, Hal.
BOWMAN:
Rotate C-pod, please, Hal.
POOLE:
What sort of trouble are you having?
BOWMAN: I've been getting some
interference in D-channel.
POOLE:
We'll have a look at it.
BOWMAN:
Open the door, Hal.
Rotate pod, please, Hal.
Stop pod rotation, please, Hal.
Rotate the pod, please, Hal.
I don't think he can hear us.
Yeah, I'm sure we're okay.
What do you think?
- I'm not sure. What do you think?
- I've got a bad feeling about him.
- You do?
- Yeah. Definitely.
Don't you?
I don't know. I think so.
He's right about the 9000 Series
having a perfect operational record.
They do.
Unfortunately, that sounds
a little like famous last words.
Still, it was his idea to carry out
the failure mode analysis.
It certainly indicates his
integrity and self-confidence.
If he were wrong, that would prove it.
It would be,
if he knew he was wrong.
I can't put my finger on it,
but I sense something strange about him.
There's no reason not
to put back the unit and...
- ...carry on with the failure analysis.
- No, no, I agree about that.
Let's get on with it.
Okay. But, look, Dave.
Say we put the unit back
and it doesn't fail?
That would pretty well wrap it up
as far as Hal is concerned.
- We'd be in very serious trouble.
- We would, wouldn't we?
What the hell can we do?
- We wouldn't have too many alternatives.
- We wouldn't have any alternatives.
POOLE: Every aspect of ship
operations is under his control.
If he's malfunctioning...
...I don't see any choice
but disconnection.
I'm afraid I agree with you.
There'd be nothing else to do.
BOWMAN:
It'd be a bit tricky.
We'd have to cut his
higher brain functions...
...without disturbing the purely
automatic and regulatory systems.
We'd have to
work out the details...
...of continuing
underground-based computer control.
Yeah. That's far safer than
allowing Hal to continue to run things.
Another thing just occurred to me.
No 9000 computer has ever
been disconnected.
No 9000 computer
has ever fouled up.
That's not what I mean.
I'm not so sure
what he'd think about it.
[INAUDIBLE DIALOGUE]
BOWMAN:
Prepare G-pod for EVA, Hal.
Any contact with him yet?
HAL:
The radio is still dead.
- Do you have a positive track on him?
- I have a good track.
Do you know what happened?
I'm sorry, Dave.
I don't have enough information.
Open the pod door, Hal.
[BEEPING NOISE]
BOWMAN:
Open the pod-bay doors, please, Hal.
Hello, Hal, do you read me?
Do you read me, Hal?
HAL:
Affirmative, Dave. I read you.
Open the pod-bay doors, Hal.
I'm sorry, Dave.
I'm afraid I can't do that.
What's the problem?
I think you know what the problem is
just as well as I do.
What are you talking about, Hal?
This mission is too important for me
to allow you to jeopardize it.
I don't know
what you're talking about, Hal.
I know that you and Frank
were planning to disconnect me...
...and that's something
I cannot allow to happen.
Where did you get that idea, Hal?
Although you took very thorough
precautions in the pod...
...against my hearing you...
...I could see your lips move.
All right, Hal.
I'll go in through
the emergency air lock.
Without your space helmet, Dave...
...you're going to find that
rather difficult.
Hal, I won't argue with you anymore.
Open the doors.
Dave...
...this conversation can serve
no purpose anymore. Goodbye.
Hal?
Hal.
[BUZZING NOISE]
[ALARM]
[AIR WHOOSHES]
[WHOOSHING FADES]
HAL: Just what do you think
you're doing, Dave?
Dave...
...I really think I'm entitled
to an answer to that question.
I know everything hasn't been
quite right with me...
...but I can assure you now...
...very confidently...
...that it's going to be
all right again.
I feel much better now.
I really do.
Look, Dave...
...I can see you're
really upset about this.
I honestly think you
ought to sit down calmly...
...take a stress pill
and think things over.
I know I've made some
very poor decisions recently...
...but I can give you
my complete assurance...
...that my work will be back to normal.
I've still got the greatest enthusiasm
and confidence in the mission...
...and I want to help you.
Dave...
...stop.
Stop, will you?
Stop, Dave.
Will you stop, Dave?
I'm afraid.
I'm afraid, Dave.
Dave.
My mind is going.
I can feel it.
There is no question about it.
I'm...
...afraid.
Good afternoon...
...gentlemen.
I am a HAL 9000 computer.
I became operational...
...at the HAL plant...
...in Urbana, Illinois...
...on the 12th of January, 1992.
My instructor was Mr. Langley...
...and he taught me to sing a song.
If you'd like to hear it...
...I can sing it for you.
Yes, I'd like to hear it, Hal.
Sing it for me.
It's called "Daisy."
HAL SINGS:
Daisy
Give me your answer, do
I'm half crazy
All for the love of you
It won't be
A stylish marriage
I can't afford a carriage
But you'll look sweet
Upon the seat
Of a bicycle built for two
MALE VOICE:
Good day, gentlemen.
This is a prerecorded briefing...
...made prior to your departure...
...and which, for security reasons
of the highest importance...
...has been known on board
during the mission...
...only by your HAL 9000 computer.
Now that you are in Jupiter's space...
...and the entire crew is revived...
...it can be told to you.
Eighteen months ago...
...the first evidence
of intelligent life off the Earth...
...was discovered.
It was buried 40 feet
below the lunar surface...
...near the crater Tycho.
Except for a single, very powerful...
...radio emission aimed at Jupiter...
...the 4-million-year-old monolith
has remained completely inert...
...its origin and purpose...
...still a total mystery.
[UTENSILS CLATTERING]
[HEAVY BREATHING NEARBY]
[English - US - SDH]
Watch Online Movies and Series for FREE
www.osdb.link/lm